<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<eml:eml xmlns:eml="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xmlns:stmml="http://www.xml-cml.org/schema/stmml-1.2" packageId="dataset-1" system="Dryad" xsi:schemaLocation="https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0 https://eml.ecoinformatics.org/eml-2.2.0/eml.xsd">
  <dataset>
    <title>Data From: TERRA REF, An Open Reference Data Set From High Resolution Genomics, Phenomics, and Imaging Sensors</title>
    <creator>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>David</givenName>
        <surName>LeBauer</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>University of Arizona</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>dlebauer@arizona.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7228-053X</userId>
    </creator>
    <abstract>
      <para>
  The ARPA-E funded TERRA REF project generating open access reference
  datasets for the study of plant sensing, genomics, and phenomics.
  Sensor data are generated by a field scanner sensing platform that
  captures color, thermal, hyperspectral, and active flourescence
  imagery as well as three dimensional structure and associated
  environmental measurements. These data are provided alongside
  traditional field methods to support calibration and validation of
  algorithms used to extract plot level phenotypes from these datasets.
</para>
      <para>
  Data were collected at a field site in Maricopa, AZ that hosts a large
  field scanner with fifteen sensors, many of which are capable of
  capturing mm scale images and point clouds at daily to weekly
  intervals.
</para>
      <para>
  These data are intended to be reused, and are accessible as a
  combination of files and databases linked by spatial, temporal, and
  genomic information. In addition to providing open access data, the
  entire computational pipeline is open source, and we enable users to
  access high performance computing environments.
</para>
      <para>
  Data Types:
</para>
      <para>
  The study has evaluated a sorghum diversity panel, biparental cross
  populations, and elite lines and hybrids from structured breeding
  populations as well as a durum wheat diversity panel. This reference
  dataset can be used to characterize phenotype-to-genotype
  associations, on a genomic scale, that will enable knowledge-driven
  breeding and the development of higher-yielding cultivars of sorghum
  and wheat. The data is also being used to develop new algorithms for
  machine learning, image analysis, genomics, and optical sensor
  engineering.
</para>
    </abstract>
    <coverage>
      <geographicCoverage>
        <geographicDescription>Maricopa Agricultural Center, Maricopa, AZ</geographicDescription>
        <boundingCoordinates>
          <westBoundingCoordinate>-111.9751</westBoundingCoordinate>
          <eastBoundingCoordinate>-111.9748</eastBoundingCoordinate>
          <northBoundingCoordinate>33.0765</northBoundingCoordinate>
          <southBoundingCoordinate>33.0745</southBoundingCoordinate>
        </boundingCoordinates>
      </geographicCoverage>
      <temporalCoverage>
        <rangeOfDates>
          <beginDate>
            <calendarDate>2017-04-13</calendarDate>
          </beginDate>
          <endDate>
            <calendarDate>2018-08-02</calendarDate>
          </endDate>
        </rangeOfDates>
      </temporalCoverage>
      <taxonomicCoverage>
        <taxonomicClassification>
          <taxonRankName>Genus</taxonRankName>
          <taxonRankValue>Sorghum</taxonRankValue>
          <taxonomicClassification>
            <taxonRankName>Species</taxonRankName>
            <taxonRankValue>Sorghum bicolor</taxonRankValue>
          </taxonomicClassification>
        </taxonomicClassification>
      </taxonomicCoverage>
    </coverage>
    <contact>
      <individualName>
        <givenName>David</givenName>
        <surName>LeBauer</surName>
      </individualName>
      <organizationName>University of Arizona</organizationName>
      <electronicMailAddress>dlebauer@arizona.edu</electronicMailAddress>
      <userId directory="https://orcid.org">https://orcid.org/0000-0001-7228-053X</userId>
    </contact>
    <methods>
      <methodStep>
        <description>
          <para>
  name,description,author,title,year,journal PlantCV,,</para>
          <para>
            <quote>Fahlgren,
  Noah</quote>
          </para>
          <para>,A versatile phenotyping system and analytics platform
  reveals diverse temporal responses to water availability in
  Setaria.,2015,Molecular plant 95th quantiles height Estimation from 3D
  Scanner,</para>
          <para>
            <quote>1. remove the lowest points, assuming that these
  represent the ground, 2. compute the height below which 95% of the
  points occur</quote>
          </para>
          <para>,</para>
          <para>
            <quote>Zongyang, Li</quote>
          </para>
          <para>,Maricopa Field
  Station Data and Metadata,2016,unpublished Manual canopy
  height,</para>
          <para>
            <quote>Canopy height estimates for each single row of 2-row
  plots. Measured in cm using meter stick, taken at the height
  representing the plot <quote>potential</quote>, ignoring stunted
  plants. The canopy height was measured as the height of the foliage
  (not the inflorescence) at the general top of the canopy where the
  upper leaves bend and/or establish a canopy surface that would support
  a very light horizontal object (imagining a light sheet of rigid
  plastic foam), discounting rare or exceptional leaves in the
  upper-most 2 or 3 percentile.</quote>
          </para>
          <para>
            <quote>Newcomb,
  Maria</quote>
          </para>
          <para>,Field measurements from Maricopa Agricultural
  Center,2016, Specific Leaf Area Leaf Punch,</para>
          <para>
            <quote>3 dried leaf
  punches, area of leaf punch = 2.01 cm2, radius = 16
  mm</quote>
          </para>
          <para>,NA,NA,NA,NA Mature leaf length,</para>
          <para>
            <quote>Selected first fully
  expanded leaf, measured length from tip to stem at the ligule, along
  the midrib. Necrotic leaf tips not included in the
  length.</quote>
          </para>
          <para>
            <quote>Newcomb, Maria</quote>
          </para>
          <para>,Field measurements from
  Maricopa Agricultural Center,2016, Mature leaf width,</para>
          <para>
            <quote>Selected
  first fully expanded leaf, measured width at the widest point along
  the length of the leaf.</quote>
          </para>
          <para>,Field
  measurements from Maricopa Agricultural Center,2016,
  ksu_plant_height,</para>
          <para>
            <quote>Select 3 plants at random, measure to the top
  of plant (max of canopy_height, panicle_height). Take average of three
  measurements</quote>
          </para>
          <para>
            <quote>Hu, Zhenbin</quote>
          </para>
          <para>,Kansas Field
  Measurements,2016, Micasense RedEdge UAV,"Collected using
  Micasense Rededge camera and sensefly ebee drone
</para>
          <para>
  Methods described in
  https://terraref.gitbooks.io/terraref-documentation/content/user/protocols-UAV.html</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Ward,
  Rick</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Unpublished UAV data collected at Maricopa Field
  Station,2016, Stem diameter at 3rd internode,Measured diameter at 3rd
  internode … between 3rd and 4th node above the ground.,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Hu,
  Zhenbin</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Kansas Field Measurements,2016, Harvest yield estimates
  Maricopa sorghum season1 mechanical harvest,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Maricopa sorghum
  season1 harvest, if range =&amp;lt;32, then each individual row cut with
  mechanical harvester (Carter mfg equipment) and weighed with onboard
  weighing system. Fresh weight and dry weight of the harvested plot (2
  rows) expressed in kg/ha assuming plot dimensions of 1.524 m width and
  3.5 m length. Dry weight of the harvested plot adjusted to 0%
  moisture. Plant moisture content (%) at harvest estimated from a
  subsample place in an uncooled greenhouse that reached a diurnal high
  temperature of 60 C before being transferred to an oven at 60 C for
  final drying. Moisture content calculated as
  (subsamplefresh-subsampledry)</para>
          <para>
            <emphasis>100/subsamplefresh.
  <quote>,</quote>Newcomb, Maria<quote>,Field measurements from Maricopa
  Agricultural Center,2016, Leaf porometer measurements for stomatal
  conductance,</quote>Sorghum season1 leaf porometer measurements were
  taken using the Decagon SC-1 Leaf Porometer, using an older unit which
  has no record of calibration. The unit was used without the desiccant
  chamber. In general, 5 measurements were made for each plot on sunlit
  leaves, the most fully developed leaves in the upper canopy that were
  sunlit. See manual description for specifications:
  http://manuals.decagon.com/Manuals/10711_Leaf%20Porometer_Web.pdf
  <quote>,</quote>Newcomb, Maria<quote>,Field measurements from Maricopa
  Agricultural Center,2016, Harvest yield estimates Maricopa sorghum
  season1 hand harvest,</quote>During Maricopa sorghum season1 harvest,
  if range &gt; 32 select plots were harvested by hand methods. Two
  1.524 m sections of each row of 2-row plots were cut by hand with a
  machete, combined and placed on a tarp, and weighed using a scale
  hanging on a tripod. The exception is the row# study where each row
  was cut and weighed separately. The cutting height was about 10 cm
  above ground-level. Fresh weight and dry weight of the harvested plot
  (2 rows) are expressed in kg/ha assuming plot dimensions of 1.524 m
  width and 3.5 m length. Dry weight of the harvested plot is adjusted
  to 0% moisture. Plant moisture content (%) at harvest estimated from a
  subsample place in an uncooled greenhouse that reached a diurnal high
  temperature of 60 C before being transferred to an oven at 60 C for
  final drying. Moisture content calculated as
  (subsamplefresh-subsampledry)</emphasis>
          </para>
          <para>100/subsamplefresh.</para>
          <para>Newcomb,
  Maria</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Field measurements from Maricopa Agricultural
  Center,2016, EBImage,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>R package for image analysis, including
  properties of object color, geometry, and texture.</para>
          <para>Pau
  G, Fuchs F, Sklyar O, Boutros M and Huber W</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,EBImage—an R
  package for image processing with applications to cellular
  phenotypes,2010,Bioinformatics Maricopa Phenotractor,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>An array
  of three types of senors mounted on the front boom of a tractor were
  used to collect multi-spectral, thermal, and height data from the
  field. Each set of sensors collected data from a single row of plants.
  Canopy reflectance was measured using a GreenSeeker (RT200 System by
  Trimble) sensor, canopy surface temperature using an Apogee S1-121
  infrared radiometer (IRT), and canopy height using a sonar proximity
  sensor. The front-boom sensor array included three replicate sets of
  sensors in 2016 to allow three rows of plants to be measured during
  each single tractor pass. Data analyses for four dates (25 Aug, 1
  Sept, 8 Sept, and 23 Sept) were completed by Matthew Maimaitiyiming
  and Wasit Wulamu, as described in their document included here.
</para>
          <para>
  ""Phenotractor data Matthew Maimaitiyiming and Wasit Wulamu
  Center for Sustainability, Saint Louis University January 6, 2017
</para>
          <para>
  The phenotractor was equipped with three types of sensors for
  measuring plant height, temperature and canopy spectral reflectance. A
  RTK GPS was installed on top of the tractor, see the figure 1.
</para>
          <para>Newcomb, Maria</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Field measurements from Maricopa
  Agricultural Center,2016, Field Scanalyzer FLIR,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>FLIR Systems
  A615 mounted on Lemnatec Field Scanner
</para>
          <para>
  Using flir2tif extractor
  https://github.com/terraref/extractors-multispectral/tree/master/flir2tif</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,NA,NA,NA,NA
  Remote Sensing Indices from Index Database,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Generated from high
  spectral resolution (&amp;lt;1nm) hyperspectral images using formulae as
  specified in the index description along with appropriate citations.
</para>
          <para>
  Accessed from http://www.indexdatabase.de December 8,
  2016</para>
          <para>Henrich, Verena</para>
          <para>Development of an
  Online indices-database: motivation, concept and
  implementation</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,2017,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>EARSeL proceedings, EARSeL, Tel
  Aviv" Field Scanner SKYE Multispectral Sensor,"Radiometers
  manufactured by Skye Instruments in the UK
</para>
          <para>
  SKYE NDVI
  https://terraref.ncsa.illinois.edu/clowder/datasets/5873a8f64f0cad7d8131af54
</para>
          <para>
  SKYE PRI
  https://terraref.ncsa.illinois.edu/clowder/datasets/5873a9174f0cad7d8131b09a
</para>
          <para>
  Measurements aggregated to plot level means using the ndvipri2csv
  extractor
  https://github.com/terraref/extractors-multispectral/tree/master/ndvipri2csv</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,NA,NA,NA,NA
  RGB texture analysis,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>This tool extracts color and texture
  features from an RGB image. The color image is converted into a dark
  green color indexed (DGCI) image and the distribution of indexed value
  computed as intensity histogram. Texture analysis is done by finding
  edges within the DGCI image and then counting the edge
  pixels.</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,NA,NA,NA,NA In-season leaf area and biomass estimates
  by destructive sampling,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Plant biomass was sampled from 1 meter
  of row on 8 June 2016 and 29 June 2016. Stems were cut by hand near
  the soil surface and placed in a plastic bag for processing. The
  number of plants in the sample and canopy height were recorded in the
  field. The samples were then taken into the lab for processing. The
  number of main stems and tillers in the entire sample were counted.
  The entire sample was used on the 8 June 2016 sampling date and a
  subsample of 5 plants on the 29 June 2016 sampling date for further
  processing. This 5-plant subsample (June 29) was weighed as well as
  the entire sample. The leaves were then separated from the stems for
  leaf area measurements. The fresh weight of the leaves and stems were
  measured for the 29 June 2016 sampling date. Leaf area was measured
  using a LiCor area meter and leaf area index (LAI) calculated by
  dividing leaf area by land area of the sample measured. The land area
  representative of the leaf area measured was 0.762 m2 for the 8 June
  2016 sampling date and 0.762 m2 times the subsample fraction for the
  29 June 2016 sampling date. The subsample fraction is defined as the
  weight of the subsample divided by the weight of the total sample. The
  leaves and stems were then placed in an oven and dried at 65 C, and
  dry weight was measured after the plant material was dry. The biomass
  of the stems and leaves on a dry weight basis were calculated from the
  measured dry weight divided by the land area representative of the
  processed sample for each sampling date as discussed above for leaf
  area. Specific leaf area (for both sample dates) and dry matter
  fraction (for the June 29 sample date) were also calculated.
  </para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Field measurements from Maricopa
  Agricultural Center,2016, Leaf surface temperature and stomatal
  conductance estimates using hand-held instruments,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Repeat
  measurements were taken using hand-held instruments to estimate leaf
  surface temperatures and leaf stomatal conductance within 6-8 select
  plots (3-4 accessions x 2 replicates) on 7 dates in mid to late June
  2017 (sorghum season 4) as part of a focused field phenotyping
  campaign related to stomatal regulation. Leaf surface temperatures
  were estimated using a FLIR TG167 Spot Thermal Camera
  (http://www.flir.com/instruments/tg167/) and an Apogee Infrared
  Radiometer Model MI-230
  (https://www.apogeeinstruments.com/ultra-narrow-field-of-view-infrared-radiometer-with-handheld-meter-mi-230/).
  Measurements were taken on sunlit leaves, targeting fully expanded
  when possible, at a distance of approximately 20 to 40 cm above the
  leaf surface. Within each plot and at each measurement time, 6 total
  measurements were taken using the FLIR and Apogee instruments, with 3
  measurements taken in each of the West and East subplot rows. Leaf
  stomatal conductance was measured using a Decagon SC-1 Porometer
  (https://www.decagon.com/en/canopy/canopy-measurements/sc-1-leaf-porometer-stomatal-conductance-measurements/).
  Within each plot and at each measurement time, 5 total measurements
  were taken using the porometer, on sunlit leaves targeting fully
  expanded leaves when possible. On each of the 7 dates when
  measurements were taken, early morning baseline equilibrium readings
  starting at 5:45 to 6:00 for one cycle through all 8 plots. Mid-day
  readings started at roughly 11:00 and continued through 3 repeat
  cycles of the 6-8 plots until roughly 15:00 to 16:00. The porometer
  was calibrated at least once in the early morning and again before the
  mid-day readings. The FLIR TG167 spot camera was tested against a
  thermal blackbody unit on 2017-06-21 (recorded 5 readings at 34.5 to
  34.6 C while the thermal blackbody recorded 33.9 C). During the later
  measurement dates, 2 plots were dropped from the repeat measurement
  cycles because they had grown out of reach for hand measurements.
  </para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Maricopa Agricultural Center
  Field Measurements and Activities,2017, Mean temperature from infrared
  images,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Clip individual or stitched thermal image to bounding
  box; compute mean temperature.
</para>
          <para>
  Computed by
  https://github.com/terraref/extractors-multispectral/tree/master/meantemp
  or similar algorithm. </para>
          <para>Zongyang, Li</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Maricopa
  Field Station Data and Metadata,2016,unpublished Whole above ground
  biomass at harvest,The whole above ground biomass expressed on dry
  matter (field) basis that was harvested per unit area.,NA,NA,NA,NA
  Protein leaf and stem measurement,Use NIR to measure protein content
  of stem and leaf during harvest,John Deere HarvestLab,Protein leaf and
  stem measurement,2019, KSU Seedling Vigor,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>1. Go through the
  field and identify five plots to use as standards that represent
  scores ranging from 1 to 5 Visit each plot 2. Go through the field to
  do seedling vigor phenotyping by compare the seedling with the
  standard plot Score Plants 3. Assign a score between 1 and 5 to each
  plot using the scale developed from standard plots</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Seedling vigor,2019,protocols.io Whole above ground
  biomass moisture content,CO_324:0000564 Whole above ground biomass
  moisture content.,NA,NA,NA,NA Ward Labs NIR Forage Analysis,Use NIR to
  measure chemistry of leaf punches,Ward Laboratories,Ward Guide,2019,
  Visual assessment of stems with desiccated leaves,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Visually
  assess number of stems (main stems or tillers) that have one or more
  leaves showing desiccation per plot, recorded as 0 to 20 stems or
  &amp;gt;20 stems.</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,NA,NA,NA,NA Visual assessment of minimum leaf
  desiccation,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Visual assessment of leaves within the plot
  showing desiccation, the estimated minimum percent leaf area
  desiccated of any single leaf among those with desiccation symptoms.
  Desiccation defined as premature cell death in younger leaves
  associated with injury or stress as opposed to
  senescence.</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,NA,NA,NA,NA Planter seed drop count,From planter
  file recorded by Kincaid precision planter laser counter and
  associated planter software. Planted length of each subplot row
  approximately 3.5 meters.,NA,NA,NA,NA Aboveground fresh biomass at
  harvest,The whole above ground biomass expressed fresh (field) basis
  that was harvested per unit area.,NA,NA,NA,NA Seedling emergence rate
  count,Ratio of the number of seedlings emerged to the number of seeds
  dropped by planter during planting. Emerged seedlings counted manually
  by subplot row. Seed drop counts recorded by Kincaid precision planter
  laser counter during planting. Planted length of each subplot row
  approximately 3.5 meters.,NA,NA,NA,NA post harvest stump count,Post
  harvest visual count of plant stumps per row within plot.,NA,NA,NA,NA
  MultispeQ v1.0 field measurements of fluorescence-based and
  absorbance-based parameters,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Measurements of multiple
  photynthesis-related parameters were taken on sunlit leaves in the
  upper canopy using the handheld MultispeQ v1.0 instrument and the Leaf
  Photosynthesis protocol macro code developed by PhotosynQ Admin.
  (https://photosynq.org/protocols/leaf-photosynthesis-multispeq-v1-0)
  Measurements made during August 2017 in the BAP experiment required a
  ladder to access leaves in the upper canopy. Repeat measurements were
  taken on select plots between approximately 10:30 and 14:30, typically
  cycling through 8 plots (4 accessions x 2 reps) several times to
  establish a time series of the parameters centered around solar noon.
  At each sampling time for each plot, 6 subsample measurements were
  taken within the plot. During August 2017 irrigation treatments were
  implemented at two levels (water-deficit zones with no irrigation and
  well-watered zones irrigated for optimal plant water status). Plots
  were selected for measurements within each of the two irrigation
  treatments. </para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Maricopa
  Agricultural Center Field Measurements and Activities,2017,
  98th_quantile_canopy_height,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>With ply file right clipped into
  plot level, compute histogram along Z-axis within the plot. Then
  integrate multiple height histogram in one plot(because we may have
  multiple scans per day) into one histogram. At last we output the 98th
  quantiles of histogram.</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,NA,NA,NA,NA Scanner 3d ply data to leaf
  angle distribution,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Leaf angle distribution is a key parameter
  to characterize canopy structure and plays a crucial role in
  controlling energy. The laser scanner in TERRA-REF gantry system is
  creating high throughput high resolution 3d plant models. We use 3d
  plant data to compute leaf normal orientation and then leads to leaf
  angle distribution. At last we generate two-parameter beta
  distribution and chi-parameter as our </para>
          <para>
            <quote>single value
  traits</quote>
          </para>
          <para>. </para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Maricopa Field
  Station Data and Metadata,2016,unpublished Scanner 3d ply data to 98th
  quantile height,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>With ply file right clipped into plot level,
  compute histogram along Z-axis within the plot. Then integrate
  multiple height histogram in one plot(because we may have multiple
  scans per day) into one histogram. At last we output the 98th
  quantiles of histogram.</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Maricopa
  Field Station Data and Metadata,2016,unpublished Scanner 3d ply data
  to panicle counting,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>uses bounding boxes information extracted
  from panicle detection extractor, with original laser scanner data, to
  create plot level panicle counting, convex hull volume/area
  data.</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Maricopa Field Station Data
  and Metadata,2016,unpublished 3D scanner to 98th quantile height,Using
  point cloud file from laser scanner and generates plot-level canopy
  height estimation(98th quantile) traits,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Zongyang,
  Li</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Maricopa Field Station Data and Metadata,2018, 3D scanner to
  leaf angle distribution,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Using 3d data from laser scanner to
  compute leaf normal orientation and then leads to leaf angle
  distribution. At last we generate leaf angle mean and variance,
  two-parameter beta distribution and chi-parameter as our </para>
          <para>
            <quote>single
  value traits</quote>
          </para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Maricopa Field
  Station Data and Metadata,2018, 3D scanner to leaf length and
  width,Using the connected component and heuristic search to find leaf.
  Then find the shortest path as the leaf length and the longest
  perpendicular path as width,Zeyu Zhang,Maricopa Field Station Data and
  Metadata,2019, 3D scanner to panicle count faster_rcnn + roughness
  threshold + convex hull,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Using 3d data from laser scanner, use
  faster rcnn do object(panicle) detection. Then use panicle bounding
  boxes, generates counting, convex hull volume/area of panicles per
  plot.</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Maricopa Field Station Data
  and Metadata,2018, Visual percent lodging estimate,Visually score
  percentage of plants in a plot that are lodged. 0 means no plant is
  lodged and 100 means all plants are completely lodged. The score is a
  subjective combination of the fraction of the plants lodged and the
  severity of lodging.,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Zhenbin Hu, Geoff
  Morris</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Phenotyping protocol for TERRA-REF,2017,protocols.io KSU
  emergence rate,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Start to record three days after first observed
  seedling emergence and visit each plot every other day. 81 - 100 %
  seeds germinated - 5, 61 - 80 % seeds germinated - 4, 41 - 60 % seeds
  germinated - 3, 21 - 40 % seeds germinated - 2, 1 - 20% seeds
  germinated - 1, 0 % No germination - 0</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,NA,NA,NA,NA Visual
  assessment of leaf dessication,Leaves were visually scored for the
  presence (1) or absence (0) of leaf dessication in the plot as judged
  by a trained indiviudal. Desication was considered tan to dark
  nectrotic tissue on a fullly emerged leaf.,NA,NA,NA,NA plant emergence
  counts,The number of plants per plot or subplot were counted during
  emergence by visual assessment on multiple dates early in the season.
  The number of plants with &gt;= 1 centimeter of green tissue above
  ground surface were counted. ,NA,NA,NA,NA Plant lodging incidence -
  Presence estimation,Plots were scored for lodging as assessed by main
  stalk leaning at an angle greater than 30 degrees from vertical.
  Scored as a binary trait.,NA,NA,NA,NA Plant basal tiller number -
  Counting,Plants were demarcated in the field with a stake for repeated
  measurements over time. Basal tiller number was counted as the number
  of tillers with a fully emerged leaf. Sorghum Crop Ontology Identifier
  CO_324:0000344
  http://www.cropontology.org/terms/CO_324:0000344/Plant%20basal%20tiller%20number%20-%20Counting/static-html?language=english,NA,NA,NA,NA
  temperature of sunlit leaf with [instrument name],</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Leaf surface
  temperature estimates of an individual pseudo-randomly selected sunlit
  leaf in the upper canopy, targeting fully expanded leaves when
  possible, using hand-held instruments. Typically 6 sub-sample
  measurements were taken within a plot, 3 of which were taken in each
  of the West and East subplot rows.</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,NA,NA,NA,NA Visual
  assessment leaf desiccation maximum,Visually assess leaves within the
  plot showing desiccation and estimate the percent leaf area desiccated
  of any single leaf among those with desiccation symptoms. The
  estimated maximum percent leaf area desiccated of any single leaf
  among those with desiccation symptoms. ,NA,NA,NA,NA Panicle height
  measurement,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Distance from soil to the top of the panicle
  (inflorescence) measured at the same time as canopy height. This is a
  visual estimate of the general top of panicles (vs top of the foliar
  canopy) for plots in which panicles had emerged, one estimate for each
  row of a 2-row plot.</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,NA,NA,NA,NA Seedling number -
  Counting,Sorghum Crop Ontology Identifier CO_324:0000176
  http://www.cropontology.org/terms/CO_324:0000176/Seedling%20number%20-%20Counting/static-html?language=english,NA,NA,NA,NA
  Crown color - Estimation,1 = green 2 = red or purple,NA,NA,NA,NA
  Aboveground fresh biomass KSU measurement,Harvest was done with a
  forage harvester (John Deere 5460 self-propelled forage harvester) at
  15 cm above of ground.Biomass was measured with at plot level by using
  two middle rows in four row plot.,NA,NA,NA,NA KSU leaf length
  measurement,1. Three plants were selected in each plot for
  measurement. 2. Leaf around 1.5 m was selected for measurement. 3.
  Wooden ruler used to measure leaf collar to end of leaf.,NA,NA,NA,NA
  KSU leaf width measurement,1. Three plants were selected from each
  plot for measurement. 2. Leaf around 1.5 m was selected for
  measurement. 3. Use wooden ruler to measure the widest place along
  leaf,NA,NA,NA,NA KSU leaf angle estimation,1. Top full extension of
  leaf was selected to measure. 2. Three plants were randomly selected
  to measure. 3. The middle leaf angle tool was used to measure the leaf
  angle. 4. Place the black bar on the right of the middle leaf angle
  tool close to the stem. Place the right bottom corner close to the
  angle between the leaf and stem.,NA,NA,NA,NA Biomass oven
  drying,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>After harvest, dry biomass in oven to constant weight.
  Then weigh the dry biomass and calculate moisture content and dry
  matter content as a fraction.</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,NA,NA,NA,NA</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Visual
  assessment of lodging at harvest on scale of 0, 1, or 2.</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Rapid
  visual assessment at the time of harvest. Some of the lodging observed
  at harvest may have occurred during the time after irrigation was
  terminated to allow the ground to dry for harvest equipment access.
  ,NA,NA,NA,NA MAC leaf width measurement,Use barcode scanning ruler to
  measure the widest part of the leaf.,NA,NA,NA,NA MAC leaf length
  measurement,Measure from leaf tip to stem along the
  midrib.,NA,NA,NA,NA KSU stem width measurement,Measurement made on the
  third internode from the ground. Use digital caliper to measure stem
  diameter.,NA,NA,NA,NA Visual assessment of bird damage to the
  grain,Visually estimate the amount of bird damage to the grain as a
  percentage of the total grain on the head.,NA,NA,NA,NA Visual rating
  of foliage greenness,Visually assess foliage greenness based on the
  proportion of dried and necrotic leaves. Rating of 1 = 0-10% leaves
  dried. Rating of 5 = &gt;75% leaves dried.,NA,NA,NA,NA KSU flowering
  time,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Record the date where 50% of the plants have one or more
  anthers showing. Three times each week (Monday, Wednesday and Friday)
  go through the field. Record the date when the plot was reached
  flowering. Flowering was defined as the date 50% of the plants have
  one or more anthers showing.</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,NA,NA,NA,NA Incident PAR Decagon
  Sunflect Ceptometer,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Measurements taken using Decagon Sunfleck
  Ceptometer. Incident radiation readings were recorded once for each
  Range, along with the time of the incident light reading, with the
  probe positioned horizontally above the canopy. Recorded values are an
  average of 5 open readings taken at that time.</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,NA,NA,NA,NA
  Ground-level PAR Decagon Sunflect Ceptometer,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Measurements
  taken using Decagon Sunfleck Ceptometer, on clear days near the time
  of solar noon. Recorded measurements are the average of 5 readings per
  plot. For each single reading, the probe is placed at ground level and
  at an angle such that the full length of the probe extends from the
  base of the main stems (planting line) of one row of a two-row plot to
  the base of the main stems (planting line) of the second row of the
  two-row plot.</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,NA,NA,NA,NA Spike height measurement,Measure
  height to top of reproductive organ,NA,NA,NA,NA Minutes after first
  incident PAR reading,Minutes after first incident PAR reading
  taken.,NA,NA,NA,NA Tiller density estimate,Tiller density estimates
  based on a small sample destructively sampled for in-season estimates
  of leaf area and biomass,NA,NA,NA,NA Dry biomass estimate,Estimated
  from in-season destructive samples of 5 to 10 plants per plot for
  in-season estimates of leaf area and biomass,NA,NA,NA,NA SLA
  calculation,Divide green leaf area by green leaf weight,NA,NA,NA,NA
  Tillers per plant estimate,Estimates of tillers per plant based on a
  small sample destructively sampled for in-season estimates of leaf
  area and biomass,NA,NA,NA,NA Plant density estimate,Plant density
  estimates based on a small sample destructively sampled for in-season
  estimates of leaf area and biomass,NA,NA,NA,NA Stalk diameter
  measurement,Stalk diameter measurements using calipers at middle of
  the stem internode immediately below the most recently fully emerged
  leaf.,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Maricopa Agricultural Center Field
  Measurements and Activities,2017, LAI estimates by destructive plant
  sampling,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Leaf area index estimates were based on a small
  sample (5 to 10 plants) destructively sampled for in-season estimates
  of leaf area and biomass. Estimated the ratio of square meters leaf
  area to square meters land area, with leaf area measured using LI-COR
  Area Meter</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Field measurements
  from Maricopa Agricultural Center,2016, Flag leaf position
  count,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Position of the flag leaf based on number of elongated
  internodes and leaves on the main stem to the flag leaf, with 1 =
  first leaf to develop, increasing in consecutive integers up to the
  flag leaf.</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Field measurements
  from Maricopa Agricultural Center,2016, Leaf to stem weight ratio
  estimate,Leaf to stem weight ratios estimates based on a small sample
  (5 to 10 plants) destructively sampled for in-season estimates of leaf
  area and fresh- and dry-weights on either a per-plant or ground area
  basis. ,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Field measurements from Maricopa
  Agricultural Center,2016, Stereo RGB data to emergence
  count,,ZongyangLi,Maricopa Field Station Data and Metadata,2020, Stem
  elongated internodes and basal tillers counts - visual repeat measures
  on marked plants,Multiple plants per plot were demarcated in the field
  early in the season using golf tees placed adjacent to the selected
  seedlings; numbers of leaves (internodes) were repeatedly counted on
  the same plant over time by permanently marking each new fully emerged
  leaf with the leaf number (1 = first leaf to develop) to capture
  temporal dynamics of growth. Numbers of tillers at each observation
  early in the season were also counted. Sorghum Crop Ontology
  Identifier CO_324:0000235
  http://www.cropontology.org/terms/CO_324:0000235/Stem%20elongated%20internodes%20number/static-html?language=english;
  Basal tiller number was counted as the number of tillers with a fully
  emerged leaf. Sorghum Crop Ontology Identifier CO_324:0000344
  http://www.cropontology.org/terms/CO_324:0000344/Plant%20basal%20tiller%20number%20-%20Counting/static-html?language=english,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Field measurements from Maricopa Agricultural
  Center,2016, Leaf polyphenolics and chlorophyll measurements: Dualex
  Scientific+ leaf-clip handheld optical meter,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>The optical
  leaf-clip meter (Dualex Scientific+) uses 5 LED light sources,
  including 1 UV-A, 1 read and 2 near-infrared (NIR) and a silicon
  photodiode detector to estimate chlorophyll content in leaves as well
  as flavonol and anthocyanin contents in the leaf epidermis.
  Measurements were taken on sunlit leaves in the upper canopy. Within
  each sampled plot, multiple subsample measurements were taken, each on
  different leaves, targeting fully developed sunlit leaves when
  possible. The instrument reports 5 measurements: 1) the temperature of
  the optical emitting head, 2) chlorophyll index (=(NIR trans. - Red
  trans.)/Red trans), 3) flavonol index (=Log(NIR fluo. excited red/NIR
  fluo. excited UV-A), 4) anthocyanin index (=Log(NIR fluo. excited
  red/NIR fluo. excited green), and 5) NBI (proprietary) nitrogen
  status, Chl/Flav ratio. </para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Maricopa
  Agricultural Center Field Measurements and Activities,2017, LAI
  estimates using LI-COR handheld LAI-2200C Plant Canopy
  Analyzer,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>The LAI (leaf area index) estimated nondestructively
  using LAI-2200C Plant Canopy Analyzer(LI-COR Inc., Lincoln, NE, USA)
  which allows users to operate under full sun condition without further
  requirements for sun angle. Measurements were conducted along a
  diagonal transect between the two plant rows of each sampled plot
  using the 45°view restrictor to hide the user from the sensor Field of
  View(FOV). Two above-canopy measurements were taken at the beginning
  and end of the plant rows; five below-canopy measurements were taken
  along the transect at even spacing by placing the sensor on the ground
  to assure maximum coverage of the plant canopy in the sensor
  FOV.</para>
          <para>
            <quote>,NA,NA,NA,NA Visual assessment of maturity stage at
  harvest,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Sorghum growth stage descriptions follow Vanderlip RL.
  1993. How a sorghum plant develops. Manhattan, KS, USA: Kansas State
  University Cooperative Extension. Growth stages grouped by the
  following categories: vegetative growth prior to flag leaf emergence;
  flag leaf fully emerged; flowering (anthesis); early, mid, and late
  grain fill. Numerical categories: 1 = Vegetative; 2 = Flag leaf; 3 =
  Flowering; 4 = Early grain fill; 5 = Mid grain fill; 6 = Late grain
  fill. Early grain fill defined as time from flowering to milk or soft
  dough stages. Mid grain fill includes soft dough stage. Late grain
  fill defined as just past soft dough to physiological maturity.
  </para>
          <para>
            <quote>,Field measurements from Maricopa
  Agricultural Center,2016, In-season per-plant leaf area and biomass
  estimates by destructive sampling,</quote>
          </para>
          <para>Five plants of median height
  selected from all plants within 1 meter section of the plot row. The
  five destructively sampled plants were processed for per-plant leaf
  area and biomass estimates. All leaves, fully emerged and emerging,
  were removed from the main stem of each of the five plants and run
  through leaf area meter to estimate total leaf area per plant (cm2).
  Leaves of all five plants were pooled to measure combined leaf fresh
  weight. Main stems of all five plants were pooled to measure combined
  stem fresh weight. Leaf and stem samples were placed in drying oven at
  60 C for two days. Dry weights of leaf and stem samples were measured
  as the combined weights of all five plants. </para>
          <para>Newcomb,
  Maria",Maricopa Agricultural Center Field Measurements and
  Activities,2017,
</para>
        </description>
      </methodStep>
    </methods>
    <dataTable>
      <entityName>metadata/germplasm.csv</entityName>
      <entityDescription>List of Sorghum genotypes ('accessions')and experiments in which they were included</entityDescription>
    </dataTable>
  </dataset>
</eml:eml>
